Comic book collection on medical themes
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
Comic book collection on medical themes
1941-2013
Pam Coll 7
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
2.5
6 boxes
The main body of this collection consists of issues of comic books from the 1940s containing "true" stories of medical heroism and biomedical progress. There are a smaller number of later comics containing history of medicine stories; comics with a public health message; comics advertising a "health" product, and some reference sources on comic books.
Hansen, Bert, 1944-
Helfand, William H.
Arrangement
The comic books are organized in three series: 1. True adventure comic books of the 1940s. 2. Other comic books including comics on public health. 3. Supplement 2017.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The first and third series were donated by Bert Hansen, Ph.D., in 2015 and 2017. The second series was donated by William Helfand.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research. Yale does not own copyright.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains issues of true adventure American comic books of the 1940s collected by Bert Hansen and arranged by title, and also a smaller collection of later American comic books on medical themes collected by historian of medicine William Helfand. Among the topics of these latter comics are drugs including the underground series, Cocaine Comix; public health; and the advertisement of health products. Major Inapak: The Space Age is a 1951 story of travel to the moon in 1984, advertising the health drink, Inapak. The medical stories in these comic books are annotated by Bert Hansen from his article, "True Adventure Comic Books and American Popular Culture in the 1940s: An Annotated Research Bibliography of Medical Heroes" (see Bibliography) or by the archivist.
The Supplement contains additional true adventure comic books from the 1940s, comic books containing medical history stories from the 1950s and 1960s, more comic books with public health messages, other comic books related to medicine, and some reference sources on comic books, including a price guide to comic books.
Biographical / Historical
The 1940s were the Golden Age of American comics. In addition to comic books on the exploits of superheroes, there was a lesser-known genre of comic books containing stories of "true" heroic adventures. Among the many other kinds of heroes in these stories were doctors, nurses, and medical scientists who braved adversities to save lives and to solve biomedical puzzles. Examples were Louis Pasteur, Edward Jenner, Alexander Fleming, Howard Florey, Walter Reed, the Mayo brothers, Clara Barton, and Sister Kenny. There were many lesser known figures as well. Several stories highlighted recent wartime achievements such as penicillin and blood banking. The stories reveal a highly positive and progressive image of medicine. The comics were collected by historian of medicine Bert Hansen, PhD, for his research and publications on mass media medical images in American popular culture.
Adventure stories; AIDS (Disease); Antismoking movement; Blood banks; Cocaine; Comic books, strips, etc. -- United States -- 20th Century; Diabetes; Drug addiction; Heroes; Medicine -- History -- Popular works; Medicine, Military; Medicine, Popular; Penicillin; Popular culture -- United States; Public health -- Popular works; Science -- Popular works; World War, 1939-1945 -- Comic books, strips, etc.; Comic books; Comics digest; Heroic comics; It really happened; Marvels of science; Negro heroes; New heroic comics; Picture stories from science; Real heroes; Real life comics; Science comics; Trail blazers; True animal picture-stories; True comics; World around us; Cocaine comix; Are your highs getting you down?; Captain America goes to war against drugs; Dennis the Menace takes a poke at poinsons; Asthma warriors; Major Inapak, the space age; Strip AIDS USA; You're smokin' now, Mr. Butts; Tresor du parc: Diabete et diabetiques; Comics: Anatomy of a mass medium; Overstreet comic book price guide
- True adventure comic books of the 1940s, 1941-1948; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  See Supplement, Subseries 1, for additional comic books of this genre.
  - Comics Digest, 1942-1943
    1 issue, Winter 1942-1943. Published by Parents' Institute, Inc., New York. This digest contains cartoon stories in black and white reprinted from True Comics "for the millions of adults who read comics."
    - Comics Digest, Winter 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Copyright 1942. Contains "Australia's Flying Doctors," 89. "Dealing with the importance of aviation in providing health care to such a dispersed population." BH
  - Heroic Comics / New Heroic Comics, 1943-1946
    General
    Heroic Comics was published in 25 issues from January 1943 to January 1947, and numbered 16 to 40. It succeeded Reg'lar Fellows Heroic Comics, numbered 1 to 15, and was continued by New Heroic Comics, numbered 41 to 97. The publisher was the Eastern Color Printing Company, New York. "Originally had superhero stories and gradually shifted to military and real-life stories." BH
    - Heroic Comics, No. 16, 1943 January (Box 1, Folder 2)
      "Daring Doctor of Mercy: Major Luther Caldwell Heidger," [13-16]. "Story of successful Connecticut doctor serving in WW II and taking risks to perform battlefield surgery under fire."
    - Heroic Comics, No. 38, 1946 September (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Stookie Allen (artist), "Copper!" [24]. "'Copper' is the title for a series on the police; this episode is about Dr. Charles Norris, New York's Chief Medical Examiner from 1918 to 1935." BH
      "Balto the Heroic Husky," [28-31]. "Balto led team of sled dogs bringing epidemic-stopping diphtheria serum to Nome, Alaska; a popular subject in comics." BH Although the issue title includes a small "New," the title did not officially change until issue Number 41.
    - New Heroic Comics, No. 44, 1947 September (Box 1, Folder 4)
      In the New Heroic Comics series, there were no major historical figures, but many stories of life-saving. Some examples with medical content are:
      "Roanoke's Volunteer Lifesavers: Wholesale Rescue," [5-8]. "During a polio epidemic in Roanoke, Va., volunteer rescue squad members deliver extra iron lungs and then have to pump them by hand through a power failure to keep patients alive." BH
      "Operation Emergency!" [9-10]. "In Birmingham, AL, a former police matron, Claudia Williams, gives artificial respiration to a child until medics arrive." BH
      "Fancy Skater: On 0ne Leg!" [11-12]. "Navy veteran, Chad Detrick, who lost a leg in war, skates in a show at Madison Square Garden to raise funds for polio victims." BH
      Sandy Toth (artist), "Mercy Flight,"[17-21]. "In Wisconsin, an amateur pilot, Earl Johnson, flies at night without instruments in order to get polio victim to a hospital in Minneapolis." BH
      Alexander Toth (artist), "Nurse Without Fear,"· [32-33]. "Nurse Esther McElveen, in Florence, S.C., saved 34 patients from flaming building only to lose her life when entering the building again for more." BH
  - It Really Happened, 1944-1948 October
    It Really Happened was published in 11 issues from 1944 to 1947 October by William H. Wise & Co., New York (copyright Best Syndicated Features, Inc.). Later published by Visual Editions, Inc.
    - It Really Happened, No. 4, 1944 [August?] (Box 1, Folder 5)
      "Dr. David Livingstone," [7-15]. "Biography of missionary doctor in Africa, working 'for the betterment of thousands of savage natives.'" BH
    - It Really Happened, No. 6, 1946 December (Box 1, Folder 6)
      "UNRRA: Man's Humanity to Man," [3-8]. "The United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration; Herbert H. Lehman resigned as NY governor to be first director general; succeeded by former NYC mayor Fiorello LaGuardia; general relief, not primarily medical." BH
      "Odd Jobs: The Fireman's Doctor," [45-47]. "Having earned an MD in 1894, Dr. Harry Archer voluntarily raced to fires to take care of the firemen for over half a century; received an award for entering a collapsed tenement to attend the injured." BH
    - It Really Happened, No. 8, 1947 April (Box 1, Folder 7)
      "Angel of Mercy: Sister Kenny," [14-20]. "The eventual recognition of the work of Australian nurse, Sister Elizabeth Kenny, for innovative treatment of polio victims." BH
    - It Really Happened, No. 11, 1947 October (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Ward[?] (artist), "Inspired Woman: Marie Curie," [3-7]. "Biography of Marie Curie, as 'one of the first great pathfinders on the road to atomic power'; this story does not mention the medical utility that other popular accounts often attributed to her work." BH
      "Fred Guardineer (artist), "Never Walk Again?" [15-18]. "Glenn Cunningham overcame childhood accident to become a world-class runner." BH
  - Marvels of Science, 1946
    Published in 4 issues, 1946 March-June, by Charlton Publications, Inc., Holyoke, Mass. "Primarily science and technology with little history or biography; while in panel format like comics, stories have few people and little dialogue, making this really an illustrated text rather than a comic." BH
    - Marvels of Science, No. 1, 1946 March (Box 1, Folder 9)
      "Wonder World of the Present & Future," 27-32. Includes "wonder drugs."
      "Dog Dead or Alive?" 46-48, is on Soviet experiments on dogs "pointing the way to blood-banking, transfusion, and plasma separation."
    - Marvels of Science, No. 2, 1946 April (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Cover of issue lacking and supplied in photocopy.
      Photograph labeled "Testing Stamina at Harvard Laboratory" [Harvard Fatigue Laboratory], 18.
      "Hero of Science," 26-27. Article without illustration on Ernst Boris Chain who shared in the Nobel Prize with Fleming and Florey for the development of penicillin.
      "Synthetic Quinine," 28-31. History of use of quinine to treat malaria; its unavailability in the war because the Japanese occupied the Dutch East Indies; development of synthetic quinine by Robert Burns Woodward and William Von Eggers Doering working for the Polaroid Corporation.
    - Marvels of Science, No. 3, 1946 May (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Bringing the Sun Inside," 15-20. "Explanation of the applied science of 'the amazing new ultra-violet ray General Electric germicidal lamp.'" BH
      "The Miracle Drug," 21-22. "Brief explanation of penicillin's discovery and development with more emphasis on science than history; mentions Fleming, Chain, and Florey, and their Nobel Prize; 'the greatest single drug known to medical science.'" BH
    - Marvels of Science, No. 4, 1946 June (Box 1, Folder 12)
      "Precipitron: Fights Dust and Infections!" 27-30. The new Westinghouse Precipitron may soon remove air-borne dust particles and protect against airborne infections in hospitals.
      "Death...to the Insects," 44-47. On the marvel of DDT.
  - Picture Stories from Science, 1947
    Only two issues of Picture Stories from Science were published, both in 1947, by School Comics, Inc., New York.
    - Picture Stories from Science, No. 2, 1947 Summer (Box 1, Folder 13)
      This issue is full of medical stories, all by Morris Nelson Sachs (writer) and Don Cameron (artist).
      "Eating for Health: The Story of Vitamins," 4-7. Narratives of James Lind (fruit prevents scurvy), Christian Eijkman (rice husks prevent beri-beri), F. G. Hopkins and Casimir Funk (theory of vitamins as accessory food factors), Charles G. King (isolation of Vitamin C); also need for other vitamins." BH
      "Watching the Stomach at Work: The Story of Dr. Beaumont," 8-10. On the experiments in digestive physiology performed by Dr. William Beaumont on Alexis St. Martin, who had a hole in his stomach allowing access to its interior.
      "The Work of the Blood: The Story of Circulation," 14-16. "Basic anatomy and physiology lesson with brief mention of William Harvey's discovery of the circulation of the blood." BH
      "Man's Unseen Foe: The Story of Germs," 19-22. "Primarily a science lesson with brief mention of Leeuwenhoek and Pasteur; viruses were mentioned without naming Iwanowski, but he appeared in the index for this story." BH
      "Fighting Germs with Germs: The Story of Vaccination and Inoculation," 25-28. "Two major narratives, from smallpox inoculation (variolation) introduced to Europe by Lady Montague through its improvement by Jenner using cowpox inoculation (vaccination) and, second, Pasteur's success with a vaccine for rabies." BH
      "The Conquest of Yellow Fever: The Story of Dr. Walter Reed," 29-32. "Detailed historical narrative of experiments with human volunteers to solve the mysterious transmission of yellow fever; Drs. Reed, Agramonte, Carroll, Lazear; volunteers William A. Dean, John R. Kissinger, John J. Moran." BH
      "Miracles of Surgery: The Story of Dr. Lister," 33. Joseph Lister's development of the carbolic acid technique to prevent deadly surgical infections.
      "Modern Medical Magic: The Story of the New Germ Killer!" 34-36. "Bowdlerized story of development of salvarsan; it 'kills the germs of our disease,' failing to mention that the disease was syphilis; Ehrlich was focus; mentioned were Koch, Fleming, Domagk, and streptomycin without naming Waksman." BH
      "Life Saving Sleep: The Story of Anaesthesia," 37-39. Narrative of the invention of ether anesthesia for surgery, with Dr. Morton, Dr. Jackson, Dr. John Warren; famous demonstration at Massachusetts General Hospital on 16 October 1846." BH
  - Real Heroes, 1942-1946
    Appeared in 16 issues, 1941 September-1946 October. Published by Parents' Magazine Press, New York, through at least issue No. 12. By issue No. 15, the comic book issues were published by Real Heroes, Inc.
    - Real Heroes, No. 3, 1942 March (Box 1, Folder 14)
      "They Said He'd Never Walk," 54-56. "Triumph of Glenn Cunningham, not medical, but personal; overcomes a childhood injury to become a star runner." Other comics also have stories on Cunningham. BH
      See Box 1, Folder 8.
    - Real Heroes, No. 4, 1942 May (Box 1, Folder 15)
      "The Story of the Red Cross." [52-57}. Story of Jean Henri Dunant, his inspiration from Florence Nightingale, his establishment of the Geneva Convention, and the Red Cross in the war today.
    - Real Heroes, No. 5, 1942 July (Box 1, Folder 16)
      "Australian Bush Nurse," [22-27]. "Biography of Sister Elizabeth Kenny; development of her therapy for polio victims." BH
    - Real Heroes, No. 7, 1942 November (Box 1, Folder 17)
      "Louis Pasteur and the Unseen Enemy," 2-25. "Story covers only pasteurization to prevent spoilage of wine." BH
    - Real Heroes, No. 9, 1943 February-March (Box 1, Folder 18)
      "Mom Chung and her 509 'Fair­ Haired Foster Sons,'" 9-14. "Biography of Dr. Margaret Chung, the first Asian-American woman to earn an MD; she raised funds for American aviators helping China resist Japanese invaders prior to the entry of U.S. into WW II." BH
    - Real Heroes, No. 15, 1946 July-August (Box 1, Folder 19)
      Two copies.
      "Plague Vanquished," [30-32]. "Discovery in 1790s by Dr. Edward Jenner that inoculation with cowpox virus (vaccination) could prevent smallpox; wrongly says General George Washington vaccinated his troops in 1778, when in fact he was using the older, pre-Jenner technique of inoculation with smallpox virus (variolation)."
      "Lifesaving Hobby," [36-38]. "Roanoke, Va., lifesaving and first-aid crew, founded by man who as a child watched helplessly as people drowned; they do water safety; also rush kids into iron lungs during 1940 polio epidemic; have inspired similar groups nationwide." BH See Box 1, Folder 4.
    - Real Heroes, No. 16, 1946 October (Box 1, Folder 20)
      "Balto of Nome," [6-8]. "The famous story of Balto leading the sled dogs through blizzards bringing diphtheria antitoxin from 1890s to 1930s to Nome to stop an epidemic; final panel shows the bronze statue of Balto in New York's Central Park." BH
  - Real Life Comics, 1943-1948
    Real Life Comics appeared in 59 issues, published from 1941 September through 1952 September by the Nedor Publishing Company, New York. Beginning with issue 32 or 33, the publisher became Visual Editions, Inc. BH
    - Real Life Comics, No. 9, 1943 January (Box 1, Folder 21)
      "Wilfred Grenfell, The Labrador Doctor," [41-46]. Story of British-born Wilfred Grenfell who served as physician to the fishermen and families living on the remote and dangerous coast of Labrador.
    - Real Life Comics, No. 11, 1943 May (Box 1, Folder 22)
      Gus Herman (artist), "The Conquest of Diphtheria," [30-36]. "Scientific development of diphtheria antitoxin from 1890s to 1930s, featuring German and French physicians and one American: Frederick Loeffler, Emile Roux, Emil August Behring, Robert Koch, Louis Pasteur, Alexandre Yersin, and William Hallock Park." BH
    - Real Life Comics, No. 13, 1943 September (Box 2, Folder 1)
      "Fever Fighter: Dr. Theobald Smith," [48-53]. "American doctor trained as a microbe hunter in Europe works for the US government and discovers ticks as the source of Texas cattle fever; this breakthrough fostered further discoveries of the role of insects in sleeping sickness and in malaria." BH
    - Real Life Comics, No. 14, 1943 November (Box 2, Folder 2)
      "The Conquest of Malaria: Ross + Grassi = Victory!" [32-37]. "Separate narratives of the work of Ronald Ross in India and Giovanni Battista Grassi in Italy, who both demonstrated the role of mosquitoes in transmission." BH
    - Real Life Comics, No. 15, 1944 January (Box 2, Folder 3)
      "Dr. Edward Jenner: Plague Fighter," [34-39]. "Classic story of Jenner's use of cowpox inoculation, i.e. vaccination, to prevent the deadly smallpox; covers his experimental trials, conservative resistance, and how much appreciation he received from around the world." BH
    - Real Life Comics, No. 17, 1944 May (Box 2, Folder 4)
      "The Story of Medicine, [7-16}. "Featured cover story on medical progress. 'Disease and ignorance formed a deadly alliance until the explorers of medicine slowly uncovered the route to human welfare.' Religion and tradition inhibit progress. Topics include: Egyptians, Galen, plague, omens, gallows, mandrake root, Pare, bezoar stone, Vesalius, gallows robbing, the royal touch, anti-dissection riots in Philadelphia and NYC, ether and asepsis in one panel each, with final panel combining battlefield medic and man in a lab; 'nostrums and amulets [have been] replaced by the certainties of science.'" BH
    - Real Life Comics, No. 18, 1944 July (Box 2, Folder 5)
      "Catherine the Great," [28-33]. "Biography of Catherine the Great of Russia as a modernizer gives prominence to her examination of the value of smallpox inoculation (variolation, mistakenly called vaccination here), even testing it on herself before risking the lives of her subjects." BH
      "Walt Whitman, Bard of Democracy," [7-12]. "Appreciation of Whitman's contribution to American values and culture; includes scenes of his nursing work in Civil War hospitals." BH
    - Real Life Comics, No. 19, 1944 September (Box 2, Folder 6)
      "The Conquest of Yellow Fever," [7-14]. "Discovery and proof that mosquitoes transmit yellow fever; use of humans for experiments with some fatalities; featuring doctors Agramonte, Carroll, Lazear (who dies a martyr to science), Finlay and Reed, and volunteer subjects Kissenger (Kissinger) and Moran."
    - Real Life Comics, No. 30, 1946 April (Box 2, Folder 7)
      "Stephen Smith," [37-40]. "Story of NYC doctor who started a reform campaign for clean cities, better housing, and public health laws; a life-long struggle against greed and corruption that was eventually successful with his laws being copied nationwide." BH
    - Real Life Comics, No. 31, 1946 May (Box 2, Folder 8)
      Nat Schachner (writer), "The Magic Mold," [26-28]. "Non-cartoon story (text with illustrations) about Dr. Ernest Chain, a refugee from Nazi Germany, whose collaboration with Howard Florey makes penicillin production possible; support from Rockefeller Foundation; 1945 Nobel Prize shared with Florey and Fleming." BH
      A.M. Froehlich (artist), "Daniel Defoe and 'Robinson Crusoe,'" [1-6]. "Biography of the great 17th-century author Defoe, with a full page about his book on the London plague of 1666." BH
    - Real Life Comics, No. 32, 1946 June (Box 2, Folder 9)
      "Dr. Gordon S. Seagrave," [20-24]. Born into a missionary family in Burma, Seagrave was raised in the U.S. and graduated from Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine. In 1922, he returned to Burma with his wife where he established a hospital and battled against disease, especially cholera. He cared for the wounded after Pearl Harbor.
    - Real Life Comics, No. 33, 1946 July (Box 2, Folder 10)
      A.M. Froehlich (artist), "Ambroise Pare: Famed Surgeon," [44-48]. "Portrayal of 16th-century French surgeon as harbinger of scientific method; 'moved a sluggish world toward scientific knowledge and cleanliness--principles on which great modern hospitals are founded.'" BH
    - Real Life Comics, No. 39, 1947 May (Box 2, Folder 11)
      "Presidential Aide: Bernard M. Baruch," [3-7]. "Financier and statesman, Baruch was adviser to many American presidents; story's medical relevance is philanthropy and research; he's credited with building a hospital and with sponsoring medical research, especially for veterans." BH
    - Real Life Comics, No. 41, 1947 September (Box 2, Folder 12)
      Nat Schachner (writer), "Master of Medicine," [30-32]. "Non-cartoon story (text with illustrations); Dr. Simon Flexner, inv1ted by John D. Rockefeller, a Baptist, to head the Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research; 'I follow the Jewish faith,' and want to pick fellow workers only by the quality of their work; story explains his research; mentions William Hallock Park." BH
      Charles M. Quinlan (artist), "Teen Age Trues," [28- 29]. "Don Molony, a young man in the US Coast Guard with medical interests, happened to be at the Empire State Building when it was struck by a plane: carried first-aid supplies to 79th floor; honored for heroism with a scholarship to the University of Michigan medical school." BH
    - Real Life Comics, No. 42, 1947 November (Box 2, Folder 13)
      "The Mayo Brothers: Doctors Courageous," [13-16]. "Biography of the sons of William Mayo, 'Doc Will' and 'Doc Charlie'; energetic and successful, they hardly seem courageous except in treating tornado victims; interesting ideas present, but each one has only a single panel; they gave $1.5 million to the University of Minnesota." BH
    - Real Life Comics, No. 44, 1948 May (Box 2, Folder 14)
      "Lucky Fellow," [8-10]. "Paratrooper Harold Russell lost both hands and used prosthetic hooks; became successful actor partly for playing amputee in 1946 film, Best Years of Our Lives. Other facts not in the story: won Oscar and later directed national organization for disabled veterans." BH
      Nat Schachner (writer), "Healer of Men," [28-30]. "Non-cartoon story (text with illustrations); biography of Waldemar Haffkine, exposing discrimination he faced as a Jew; his career was supported by Metchnikoff and by Pasteur; worked on epidemic diseases in India, developing cholera vaccine and then one for plague." BH
  - Science Comics, 1946
    Science Comics was published in 5 issues, all appearing in 1946, by Humor Publications, Inc., Springfield, Mass.
    - Science Comics, No. 1, 1946 January (Box 2, Folder 15)